With a title like that, I'd better
deliver. There's been some back and
forth going on around a particular
supplement and its increased risk of
cancer coming out of a combination study
taking two randomized control trials and
pooling the data to identify a
potentially cancer-causing effect of
vitamin B, specifically vitamin B9,
although B6 and B12 were also checked
out. The overall study is this one, and
included almost 7,000 participants with
heart disease. randomly assigned to
consume folic acid. That's vitamin B9,
vitamin B6 and B12. So that's one group.
The other three groups consumed folic
acid and vitamin B12 or vitamin B6 only
or a placebo, none of the vitamins. Then
they assessed cancer mortality rates in
these people over 6 years, although they
consumed these vitamins over only three
years. So what happened? Nothing. No one
developed cancer. and died from it. The
end. Obviously, some people died from
cancer at a greater rate than normal. If
we pop open that data, there's cancer
incidents, as in the number of cancer
cases on top, and we have the actual
death from cancer as well as overall
mortality and non-cancerous mortality.
We have the four vitamin B conditions up
top, including placebo. Then on the
right, we have the hazard ratio. That
tells us in a relative sense if there's
an increase in cancer relative to
another group. There's two comparisons.
So folic acid versus all the other
groups not including folic acid combined
and the vitamin B6 versus all the other
groups not including vitamin B6.
Generally if the values are above 1.0
that indicates increased cancer. But
these parentheses tell us the margin of
error in the results. For example,
although the top right condition, the
vitamin B6 versus nonvitamin B6 groups
indicates a 1.07, which is increased
risk, the confidence intervals fall
below one with a 0.92. So, we couldn't
say that we have detected an effect
because we don't have enough precision
in the results. On the other hand, if we
look at the folic acid comparison,
there's several instances of worry like
overall cancer incidence and overall
cancer mortality. Cancer cases increase
about 21% and the death from cancer
increases 38%. Scary, especially since
folic acid is found all over the place,
including regular multivitamins.
Unfortunately, we likely don't have
enough data to tease out which cancer
people are most prone to. And as a quick
mention, none of the vitamin B6
comparisons indicated risk. So this
falls squarely on vitamin B9, folic
acid. Okay, so folic acid increases
cancer sort of. We'll get into my
hesitation in a bit, but let's
understand what's been proposed by the
researchers as to how folic acid
increases cancer. They mentioned that
folic acid may stimulate the growth of
neoplasms. These are abnormal growths in
the body, although not always cancerous,
but they can often go undetected and
folic acid may stimulate cancerous prone
neoplasms to develop more quickly. In
addition, your immune system is quite
adept at eliminating cancerous cells and
it does that through two branches of
immunity, the adaptive and the innate
immune system. One of the first
anti-cancerous defense systems is
through a group of cells called the
natural killer cells. There is evidence
that high folic acid exposure can be
cytotoxic, meaning it kills NK cells.
Here's what's especially concerning
about this study. The two randomized
controlled studies included were
performed in Norway where food is not
fortified with folic acid, unlike many
other countries like the USA where foods
are fortified with folic acid. So these
people were presumably already consuming
less folic acid than people in countries
consuming it by consequence through food
fortification. In addition, a known
carcinogen smoking was slightly lower in
the folic acid conditions at baseline.
Even so, there are some hesitations
about overinterpreting these data. And
there's also a strong cautionary tale to
tell in relation to stopping folic acid
completely. For one, other researchers
have pushed back on this study some. For
example, they reference other studies
like the hope study. Maybe they're
hoping these results aren't true.
That was a weak one. Anyway, this hope
study also had people consume folic
acid. And although the study wasn't
focused on cancer, they did look at
cancer incidents, too. And they found no
relationship between folic acid and
cancer. In addition, these participants
were in countries where folic acid
fortification in food is common. So now
we have disagreeing takes from
randomized control trials. How do we
reconcile this? Okay, I'm about to go
off on a statistical rabbit hole. If
you're not interested, skip to this
timestamp and we'll get you closer to
the main takeaways. For the rest of you
nerds, let's discuss. I mentioned that
the hope study wasn't focused on cancer
and that's outlined in the fact that the
cancer was a secondary outcome meaning
they recruited participants to detect a
cardiovascular effect not a cancer
effect. In such a case the statistics
nor the amount of data may be sensitive
enough to detect a cancer effect if
there were one. In addition, the first
trial that we went over had a power of a
mere 61% which is very low. That means
there is an almost 40% chance of not
detecting an effect when there is one.
And yet they still detected a cancer
effect. Now considering that the Hope
study had fewer participants and the
Ebbing study, that's the first study had
only 60% power with almost 2,000 more
participants, it might be expected not
to detect an effect in the Hope trial.
These are educated speculations, but
there's certainly plausible explanations
for why one study shows an effect and
the other doesn't. I should still point
out that other critiques of these
studies is that they're shorter studies.
They're not epidemiological, which means
that study can run for 20 or more years.
And there's mixed evidence from other
analyses on the relationship between
folic acid and cancer. Some indicate a
mild increase in risk and some show no
relationship or even beneficial
relationships. This suggests to me that
there may be some mediating factor that
we're not taking into account or
something else is going on that we may
be missing. But that doesn't mean that
we can't get some actual takeaways here.
And they don't involve stopping folic
acid consumption. as weird as that might
sound in the context that we're
discussing. Before that, if you've ever
had your MTHFR gene checked or if you'd
like to have a deeper dive into this
investigation, you can access the full
version of this video that you're
watching, including a written research
review, the hundreds of other research
reviews and videos in my Physionic
Insiders membership. Also includes live
sessions, uh private podcast, and more.
Check it out. It's in the description
box, and I'd really love to have you
there. Okay. So, how do we think about
all this? Look, if you don't consume
folate or folic acid, you are also more
prone to cancer. Yes, that's right.
Consuming it might increase cancer risk,
but not consuming it will also increase
cancer risk because it's a critical
player in building DNA molecules. As
your DNA is damaged and needs to be
replaced, which happens all the time, by
the way, folic acid allows you to
replace those broken pieces. Also,
during development, your nervous system
requires folate to mature from its early
stages called the neural tube.
You also won't be producing mature red
blood cells leading to a lack of oxygen
delivery across the body. So, yeah,
folate of some form is absolutely
critical. Now, how do we balance this
correctly? Well, the studies that we've
been referencing have been using pretty
high doses of folic acid, which is more
easily absorbed than the naturally
occurring folate. In fact, they use
double the recommended daily allowance.
The RDA for folate is 400 micrograms. So
the natural conclusion is to consume
enough folate and folic acid to achieve
near the recommended daily levels, but
not to over consume for long periods of
time, even as short as a few years. I'd
also consider paying attention to
fortified foods. Most are minimally
fortified, so they're well below the
RDA. But there are some foods that
contribute the full RDA value, like
certain fortified cereals, although
others have lower levels. I'd also check
your supplements. If it's supplied the
entire RDA as folic acid or if it
supplies part of it as folate, which is
less absorbed. If you generally consume
whole foods, you probably don't need to
be supplementing anyways. As plenty of
foods have good levels of folate, like
leafy greens, legumes, asparagus,
sunflower seeds, and for meat eaters,
liver is especially potent. This is a
non-exhaustive list. FYI, if I didn't
mention your favorite food, that's
because I'm not a listicle. So the
takeaway here is one, excess folic acid
is linked to increased cancer risk, but
eliminating folic acid or folate
entirely also leads to serious health
consequences. Number two, check your
supplements and general folate folic
acid consumption and try to hit just
below or at the RDA of 400 micrograms
depending on if you eat a lot of
fortified foods. Moderation is not just
key, but especially critical in this
situation, except in the context of
physionic videos, which you should
always overconume. It's unconfirmed if
they cause cancer, but they're a good
time at least right